A Guide to the Samuel A. Mann Papers, 1863, 1914
Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
Samuel A. Mann Papers, 1863, 1914
Special Collections and Archives, Johnston Memorial Library, Virginia State University
1959-6
There are ca. 200 items in this collection.
This collection contains personal, business, and agricultural records of a white farmer from Matoca in Chesterfield County, Va. Included are a number of thorough diaries detailing his daily activities.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift to Virginia State University by Charles E. Mann in 1959.
Biographical/Historical Information
Samuel A. Mann was born in Matoaca, Virginia in 1842. He grew up on a small tract of land that the family farmed. The Mann's were not slave holders and according to the 1860 United States Census, Samuel Mann's father Randolph was a Millwright.
In January 1862 Samuel Mann left home and joined the Southside Heavy Artillery unit of Virginia Volunteer. This unit was made up exclusively of men from Chesterfield County Virginia. In February Mann was elected Third Corporal. Samuel Mann served in the Confederate Army for three years. During that time he was involved in a number of battles including "Drewery's Bluff" which was fought in May of 1862. Samuel Mann remained in the military until he was paroled at Appomattox in 1865. Samuel Mann returned to Matoaca and the family farm in the spring of 1865. In 1870 Samuel Mann was elected tax assessor in the village of Matoaca. During the next thirty years Samuel Mann held a number of elected and appointed positions in Chesterfield County Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
This collection contains a number of diaries detailing Samuel A. Mann's daily activities, his work as a county assessor, and other activities in the village of Matoaca. There is some material that couments the African- American population and, in particular, political activities and land holdings.
Organization
SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE
Letters and postcards, all having to do with personal and business matters. Arranged chronologically 1874-1914. Some material about school. (Container 1)
SERIES II. FINANCIAL
Personal and tax receipts arranged by type, 1871-1892. (Container 1)
SERIES III. SURVEYS
Land surveys for two schools, one located on river Road, the other in Clover hill, 1884. (Container 1)
SERIES IV. LEGAL DOCUMENTS
Copy of promotion order for Emmett J. Mann from second Lt. To first Lt., Army of Northern Virginia, 1863. (Container 1)
SERIES V. BUSINESS RECORDS
Records of wages paid in 1879. (Container 1)
SERIES VI. PRINTED
Red Man Certificate. (Container 1)
SERIES VII. DIARIES
Eight boxes of diaries concerning a time period from 1869-1914, the diaries are a record of life in the village of Matoaca concerning mostly, farming practices, home life, some political observations and some information concerning the black community. (Containers 2-9)
Contents List
- SERIES I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - Correspondence 1874 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Correspondence 1877-1878 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Correspondence 1881 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Correspondence 1882 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Correspondence 1887 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Correspondence 1889 (Box-folder 1:6)
  - Correspondence 1909 (Box-folder 1:7)
  - Correspondence 1914 (Box-folder 1:8)
- SERIES II. FINANCIAL
  - Receipts Personal 1877 (Box-folder 1:9)
  - Receipts Personal 1879 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Receipts Personal 1882 (Box-folder 1:11)
  - Receipts Personal 1887 (Box-folder 1:13)
  - Receipts Personal 1888 (Box-folder 1:14)
  - Receipts Personal 1892 (Box-folder 1:15)
  - Receipts Personal 1907 (Box-folder 1:16)
  - Receipts Personal n.d. (Box-folder 1:17)
- SERIES III. SURVEYS
  - Clover Hill School Lot 1884 (Box-folder 1:18)
  - School Plat 1884 (Box-folder 1:19)
- SERIES IV. LEGAL DOCUMENTS
  - Army of Virginia Promotion 1863, Copy (Box-folder 1:20)
  - Land Deed 1879 (Box-folder 1:21)
  - Taxes and Revenue 1871 (Box-folder 1:22)
  - Taxes and Revenue 1877 (Box-folder 1:23)
  - Taxes and Revenue 1883 (Box-folder 1:24)
  - Taxes and Revenue 1890 (Box-folder 1:25)
  - Taxes and Revenue n.d. (Box-folder 1:26)
- SERIES V. BUSINESS RECORDS
  - Pay Record 1879 (Box-folder 1:27)
- SERIES VI. PRINTED
  - Certificate 1881 (Box-folder 1:28)
  - News Clippings 1964 (Box-folder 1:29)
- SERIES VII. DIARIES 1869-1914
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1869, 3 books (Box 2)
  - Diaries Feb-Dec 1870, 4 books (Box 2)
  - Diaries March-Dec 1871, 4 books (Box 2)
  - Diaries Feb-Aug 1872, 5 books (Box 3)
  - Diaries Jan-Sept 1873, 1 book (Box 3)
  - Diaries Jan-June 1873, 1 book (Box 3)
    Account book, also includes 1874,1878,1880
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1876, 1 book (Box 3)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1878, book (Box 4)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1880, 1 book (Box 4)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1881, 1 book (Box 4)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1882, 1 book (Box 4)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1883, 1 book (Box 4)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1884, 1 book (Box 5)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1885, 1 book (Box 5)
  - Diaries Jan 1886, 1 book (Box 5)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1887, 1 book (Box 5)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1888, 1 book (Box 5)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1889, 1 book (Box 5)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1890, 1 book (Box 6)
  - Diaries Jan-June 30 1891, 1 book (Box 6)
    Includes some 1890, also statements of accounts, 1887-1888
  - Diaries July-Dec 1891, 1 book (Box 6)
  - Diaries June 16-Dec 1892, 1 book (Box 6)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1893, 1 book (Box 6)
  - Diaries Sept-Dec 1893, 1 book (Box 7)
  - Diaries Nov-Dec 1894, 1 book (Box 7)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1895, 1 book (Box 7)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1896, 1 book (Box 7)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1897, 1 book (Box 7)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1898, 1 book (Box 7)
  - Diaries Jan-Feb 28 1899, 1 book (Box 8)
  - Diaries March-Dec 1898, 1 book (Box 8)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1900, 1 book (Box 8)
  - Diaries Jan-June 14 1901, 1 book (Box 8)
  - Diaries June 15-Dec 1901, 1 book (Box 8)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1902, 1 book (Box 8)
  - Diaries Jan-July 17 1903, 1 book (Box 8)
  - Diaries July 18-Dec 1903, 1 book (Box 8)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1904, 1 book (Box 8)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1905, 1 book (Box 8)
  - Diaries Jan-Feb 28 1906, 1 book (Box 9)
  - Diaries March-Dec 1906, 1 book (Box 9)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1907, 1 book (Box 9)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1908, 1 book (Box 9)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1909, 1 book (Box 9)
  - Diaries Jan-Nov 1910, 1 book (Box 9)
  - Diaries Dec 1910, 1 book (Box 9)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1911, 1 book (Box 9)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1912, 1 book (Box 9)
  - Diaries Jan-Dec 1913, 1 book (Box 9)
  - Diaries Jan-16 July 1914, 1 book (Box 9)
  - Land Books & Indexes n.d. (Box 10)
  - Diaries 1871-1872, 1 book (Box 10)
  - Diaries - Name n.d., 1 book (Box 10)
  - Index to Land Books 1880 (Box 10)